Guide to the Lucie Ruth Weinstein Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lucie Ruth Weinstein papers
1919-2000
MS 1807
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Correspondence, writings, clippings, and photographs documenting Lucie Weinstein's efforts to establish a memorial to Jewish victims from Bad Berleburg who died in the Holocaust, and efforts by family members to assist and trace relatives in Europe during and after World War II.
Weinstein, Lucie Ruth
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lucie Weinstein, 2002.
Associated Materials
Lucie W. Holocaust Testimony (HVT-6), Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Lucie Weinstein (nee Krebs) was born in Bad Berleburg, Germany, in 1924. She was expelled from school in 1938 for being a Jew. While her parents awaited permission to emigrate to America, and fearing for the safety of their children, they sent Lucie and her brother and sister to live with the Lindheim family (Lucie's mother's sister's family) in Belgium. After two years, the children went back to Germany. Their parents, with the help of relatives in the United States, had finally obtained permission to emigrate. The family arrived in America in 1941. Almost all of the remaining members of both their immediate and extended families, who remained in Germany and elsewhere in Europe, died in the Holocaust. Lucie married Stanley Weinstein in 1951. She travelled to Japan with him and while living there, attended the Tokyo University of the Fine Arts. She later earned a Masters degree from Harvard, and a Ph.D. from Yale University, specializing in Buddhist art. She taught art history at Southern Connecticut State University for twenty-five years. In the late 1990s, Lucie worked to establish a memorial to Jewish victims from Bad Berleburg who died in the Holocaust. The monument was dedicated in Bad Berleburg in May 2000.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, clippings, and photographs documenting Lucie Weinstein's efforts to establish a memorial to Jewish victims from Bad Berleburg who died in the Holocaust, and efforts by family members to assist and trace relatives in Europe during and after World War II.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Holocaust memorials -- Germany; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) -- Personal narratives; Bad Berleburg (Germany); Weinstein, Lucie Ruth
- Original Accession
  - Bad Berleburg
    - Jews deported during World War II [lists of and articles], 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Elementary school [naming of], 1988-1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Synagogue [articles], 1995, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dick, Heinz [poem about Krystallnacht], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Drei Jahre illegal in Dritten Reich 1942-1945" [account of the brother of Irma Ruelf, distant relative of Lucie Weinstein. He lived underground in Germany during World War II.], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family correspondence and documents [includes correspondence of Julius Frank, whose wife was Lucie's mother's sister, regarding his efforts to trace Lindheim family members and property in Belgium and to assist persons who wanted to escape Germany], 1919-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 8)
  - Krebs, Adele [Lucie Weinstein's aunt; poem written while Krebs was in Theresienstadt], 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Krebs, Adolf, Betti, Ruth [correspondence to Lucie Weinstein's father's brother (Adolf), who resided in England, from his wife (Betti) and daughter (Ruth) in Germany. The latter died in concentration camps.], 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memorial
    - Inspiration for memorial [explained in letter], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dedication
      - Invitation and program, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Newspaper coverage, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Photographs [see the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database]
      - Videos, 2000
        General
        See: Inventory Box 4
        See: Inventory Box 3
        General note
        See: Inventory Box 2
      - Weinstein, Lucie, speech [English and German], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Desecration [articles], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Reaction to [articles and correspondence], 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Riedesel, Rikarde [worked with Lucie in her efforts to establish a memorial], 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Weinstein, Lucie
    - Biographical, 1924, 1937-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Photocopies of photographs [see also the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database], 1920s-1940s, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Reminiscences of childhood and adult life [published in anniversary book of Johannes Althusius Gymnasium in Bad Berleburg], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Videos of memorial dedication, 2000
    - Video 1 [master; restricted] (Box 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Video 2 [master; restricted] (Box 3)
    - Video 3 [use copy; edited version of Videos 1 and 2] (Box 4)